start with four positive real numbers a
b c and d and suppose that a times D is
greater than b times C then draw a right
triangle with legs of length a d and AC
rotate a copy of this triangle and scale
by the value B over a creating a right
triangle with legs of length b c and b d
place the two triangles so they meet at
complementary angles connect the apexes
of these two triangles with a straight
line to create a third triangle as shown
here we can use the Pythagorean theorem
on the original two triangles to find
two of the side lengths of this new
triangle the first is B times the square
root of c squared plus D Squared while
the second is a times the square root of
c squared plus D Squared because the
first two triangles fit together along
complementary angles we know that the
blue triangle is also a right angle
triangle so we can then use the
Pythagorean theorem to find the final
side length or the hypotenuse of the
blue triangle to be this square root of
a squared plus b squared times the
square root of c squared plus D Squared
the resulting diagram is a trapezoid we
can then draw another right triangle in
the upper right corner to complete this
trapezoid to a rectangle one side length
of this new right triangle is a D minus
BC because it's equal to the difference
of the two parallel side lengths of the
original two triangles the other side
length of the new right triangle is AC
plus BD because that length is equal to
the sum of the two adjacent side lengths
of the original two right triangles
but now we can apply the Pythagorean
theorem one last time to this new right
triangle from this theorem we see that
the square root of a squared plus b
squared times the square root of c
squared plus D Squared all squared must
equal the quantity AC plus b d squared
plus the quantity a D minus BC squared
if we Square the left side we get the
resulting formula that the quantity a
squared plus b squared times the
quantity c squared plus d squared equals
the quantity AC plus b d squared plus
the quantity a D minus BC squared this
theorem says that the product of two
sums of squares must be a sum of squares
itself the result is of particular
interest when all the numbers a b c and
d involved are actually integers and not
just real numbers in this case we call
this diaphanes's sum of squares identity